<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "http://www.cs.stolaf.edu/lib/SpecML/SpecML.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet
   href="http://www.cs.stolaf.edu/lib/SpecML/SpecMLToHTML.xsl"
   type="text/xsl"?>

<spec>
<title>MainMenuState Class Specification</title>
<header>This class handles the creation and management of the main menu.</header>
<credits>Joe Jung, Eric Brichetto</credits>

<class name="MainMenuState">

<superclass name="GameState">
</superclass>

<variables>
<var name="background" type="int">The ID of the background texture, to be displayed using loadTexture and draw().</var>
<var name="currentMode" type="MenuMode">An enum representing the currently opened submenu. The possible names are identical to those displayed in-game in the menu, with the exception of Home (which represents the default main menu screen).</var>
<var name="screen" type="MenuScreen*[]">An array of pointers to MenuScreen widgets. </var> 
<var name="party" type="Party&amp;">A reference to a Party. </var>
</variables>

<constructors-list>

<constructor>
<desc></desc>
<arguments>
<arg name="input" type="InputSystem&amp;">A particular GameState.</arg>
<arg name="party" type="Party&amp;">A Party of characters holding Ardy and Elma.</arg>
</arguments>
<statechange>Initializes GameState with input and party with party. Loads images/menubackground.pam as a texture ID into background. Sets currentMode to MENU_HOME and creates a new HomeScreen object, StatusScreen object, and EquipScreen object for screen[MENU_HOME], screen[MENU_STATUS], and screen[MENU_EQUIPMENT], respectively. Shows the Home menu and hides the others, and sets the inherited finished variable to false.</statechange>
</constructor>

</constructors-list>

<destructor>
<desc>Deletes the menu objects pointed to by each element in the screen array.</desc>
<statechange></statechange>
</destructor>

<methods-list>

<method name="onOpen" returntype="void">
<desc></desc>
<arguments>
<arg name="none"></arg>
</arguments>
<statechange>Sets the inherited variables running and finished to true.</statechange>
</method>

<method name="onClose" returntype="void">
<desc></desc>
<arguments>
<arg name="none"></arg>
</arguments>
<statechange>Sets the address pointed to by NextState equal to 0.</statechange>
</method>

<method name="onFrame" returntype="void">
<desc>Manages the drawing of and switching between menus from MenuMode, and returning to exploration mode.</desc>
<arguments>
<arg name="none"></arg>
</arguments>
<statechange>Sets running to false if the 'x' key is pressed on the Home menu. Passes between different MenuModes and redraws the background texture each frame.</statechange>
</method>

</methods-list>

</class>

</spec>
